You're covered in bruises.
你这一身伤
What on earth happened?
怎么弄的
I tripped over something and fell.
不小心摔的
If so, then Chief Shen
那大阁领
was being quite careless.
可就太不小心了
What I'm trying to say is,
我的意思是说呀
he didn't take good care of you.
他也没照顾好你
You know,
我跟你们说啊
when women get beaten up at home,
一般在家挨打的女人
they tend to say that.
都这么说
Am I right?
对不对
Absolutely.
对
Lord.
大人大人
What happened to you?
您这是怎么了
Step aside, step aside.
闪闪闪 闪开闪开
Please, sit down.
快快快 坐坐坐
Take it easy.
慢点慢点
What happened to you?
这怎么弄的这是
Where's your injury?
伤哪儿了
Easy, easy.
慢点慢点慢点
How did you get injured?
这伤哪儿了您这是
What happened?
怎么弄的这是
I tripped.
不小心摔 摔的
What? You too?
您也是摔的
Poker face!
江古板
I just wanted to enjoy the play.
我就是想看场戏嘛
It was halfway through the play
那大面才唱一半
when my father dragged me back.
我爹就给我捉回来了
It must have been that poker face!
肯定是那个江古板
You know,
你说
was that poker face!
那个江古板
sent by Wu Taiming
是不是老吴
to make us suffer?
派来折磨我的
What did I do
我到底是哪儿
to upset him?
得罪他了呢
My father says,
我爹说了
there's no problem that
就没有一锭金元宝
can't be solved with a gold ingot.
解决不了的事
If one ingot isn't enough,
如果一锭不行的话
then make it two.
那就两锭
Chuichui.
垂垂
Honestly, I can't help you with this.
这个事我真的帮不了你
Because Chichi
小池池呢
asked me to meet her
今日约我在
at Guangyue Restaurant today.
广悦酒楼里面见面
I have to go.
我要走了
You fickle little toots.
你个见异思迁的东西
Xing.
六娘
You can justify
你这
by saying your head got bumped,
头上可以说是撞伤的
but how did you
那你这腿上
hurt your leg?
是如何受伤的
Did the White Death trouble you?
不会是白无常欺负你吧
No, no, not at all.
不是不是不是
I have to go.
我走了我走了
Boss!
老板
One pancake, please.
来个饼
What a lovely day today!
今天天气真好
Enjoy your pancake.
来 拿好您的饼
Thanks. Put it on my tab.
谢谢 记我账上
Sure.
好
Lady Lu.
陆书令史
Poker face,
江古板
cut to the chase,
你就明说吧
how much do you want?
你到底想要多少
What you gave me
你给的
is quite generous.
足够多了
This way up.
来 上
Look over there.
你看那边
Chuichui!
垂垂
Daddy,
爹爹
can I have a gold ingot?
给我一锭金子吧
Sweetie,
垂垂
there's no need for gold
你买这种穷小子
to acquire a lad like him.
哪使得了金子呀
A string of copper coins would suffice.
那有一串通宝就足矣了
Take this.
给
No,
不行
I want a gold ingot.
我就要一锭金子
Miss,
小娘子
I'll be at your service now.
以后我就是你的人了
No need.
不用
I have plenty of servants.
我家奴仆够多了
A man shouldn't spend his life
男子汉一辈子
serving others.
伺候人怎么行
He should do more meaningful things,
要去做更有意义的事情
like protecting others.
保护更多人
Let's go.
走吧
[Chi,]
小池池
[Our friendship comes from]
你我以文会友
[many private letters.]
闺中书信多时
[Today, we finally get to meet.]
今日终于要见面了
[I'm a bit nervous.]
还真有些紧张
[I wonder what kind of]
不知你是一位怎样
[fair and delicate]
如花似玉的
[maiden are you?]
美娇娘呢
Miss,
小姐
Yan the Erudite fell ill.
颜博士突发急病
Please head back to check on him.
请您快回府上看看
[My father is unwell.]
家父急病
[Talk later.]
改期再叙
[I hope you understand.]
万望见谅
Father!
爹
How are you, father?
爹你怎么样了
It's truly a challenge to meet
如今本相想见夫人一面
Lady Yan these days.
那真是不容易啊
Even more so
本相要想听夫人
to get a few honest words
讲两句实话
from Lady Yan.
那更是难于登天了
My lord, I wouldn't dare.
六娘不敢
You wouldn't dare?
不敢
You knew very well
你明知本相
I had you marry into the Shen Family
让你嫁到沈府
for a specific purpose.
是因为何事
Yet every day,
你却天天
you keep bringing matters like
把沈渡一日三餐
what Shen Du eats or drinks
吃什么喝什么这等琐事
to fool me.
拿来打发我
My Lord,
张相
I know once I come here,
六娘自知入得沈府
I must share your burden
就要替张相分忧
and keep watching Shen Du.
时刻探听沈渡的信息
However, Xing is merely a
可六娘在沈府
household woman
也不过是一介
in the Shen residence.
深闺妇人
What I could uncover
所能打探到的
is limited to his daily meals.
也不过是三餐琐事
Yet secret messages
听闻谍报信息
come from details.
讲究见微知著
Xing fears missing anything,
六娘唯恐遗漏
so I must attend to every detail.
只好事无巨细
If my lord finds it's insufficient,
如若张相仍觉不够
then next month's report
那么下月密报
will include his daily routines,
六娘便将起居时辰
bathing habits,
沐浴情况
and intimate moments...
行房
Shut it!
住口
You, a young lady,
你一个女儿家家的
how could you be so indiscreet!
怎能如此口不择言
Yan the Erudite,
颜博士 颜博士
this is the fine girl
这便是你
you've raised!
教养出来的好女儿
Apologies, prime minister.
张相恕罪
Please forgive her.
张相恕罪啊
My fault for her bad manners.
是我教女无方
I am to blame.
教女无方啊
Xing was being incompetent,
六娘不成器
unable to gather useful intelligence.
未能探听到有用的情报
I beg for your forgiveness.
还请张相
Please do not blame my father.
不要迁怒于父亲
Xing,
六娘啊
I understand that
老夫知道
once a girl gets married,
这女儿家一旦嫁了人
she takes her husband as her world.
便以夫为天
In her eyes and heart,
这眼里心里啊
there's no one but him.
全是身边人
Even if she's wronged,
即使受了委屈
she has to endure it silently.
也要自行咽下
However,
可是
what a woman fears most is having
这女儿家最怕的就是
a wolf in sheep's clothing by her side.
枕边人是中山狼啊
As for the case regarding the Shens,
沈府一案
it created quite a stir back then.
当年轰动朝野
You were still quite young,
你那时尚幼
but you must have heard about it.
但是你应该听说过
Do you know
你可知道
who dealt the final blow
给沈家最后一击的
to the Shen Family?
是谁吗
It was Shen Du himself.
就是沈渡
Chief Shen,
大阁领
I have ascertained that
经属下查明
any case reviewed by Her Highness
凡经过太皇太后御批
for over ten years
十年以上的旧案
has its evidence archived
证物存档
within the Imperial Secretariat.
都放在麟台秘书省
Imperial Secretariat?
麟台
But it's entrenched in power struggles,
但秘书省势力盘根错节
and it has always been heavily guarded.
麟台又向来戒备森严
Even we, the Imperial Guard,
哪怕是内卫
may not approach it without just cause.
都不得无故靠近
No worries.
无妨
As long as the items are there,
只要东西在
there will be a way to obtain them.
自然有办法拿到
Yes.
是
Additionally,
此外
my lady returned to the Yan residence tonight.
夫人夜间回了趟颜府
Coincidentally,
不过巧的是
Prime minister Zhang also went there tonight,
张相今晚也去了颜府
and he didn't take his own carriage.
而且没有坐相府的车辇
Instead, he used a regular sedan carriage.
反而是常规软轿
Got it.
知道了
I'll wait outside, my lord.
那属下在门外候着
I hereby report!
我检举
The traitor Shen Bingzhu's son, Shen Du
罪臣沈秉烛之子沈渡
accuses my father
检举我父
of colluding with foreign powers
里通外国
and committing treason!
叛军通敌
I hereby report!
我检举
The traitor Shen Bingzhu's son, Shen Du
罪臣沈秉烛之子沈渡
accuses my father
检举我父
of colluding with foreign powers
里通外国
and committing treason!
叛军通敌
I hereby report!
我检举
The traitor Shen Bingzhu's son, Shen Du
罪臣沈秉烛之子沈渡
accuses my father
检举我父
of colluding with foreign powers
里通外国
and committing treason!
叛军通敌
[Chief Shen,]
大阁领
[what's the point of mocking me?]
因何讥讽于我呀
[Yes, I murdered my own kin,]
我是谋杀亲子
[but what about you?]
可你呢
[You reported your own father.]
告发亲爹
[You are no better than me.]
你我分明是一种人啊
[Father!]
父亲
[I had no choice]
当年的路
[but to take that path back then.]
我没得选
[But now, as long as]
但如今
[I could enter the Imperial Secretariat,]
只要我能顺利进入麟台
[I could obtain the]
就能拿到当年的
[letters of treason.]
通敌书信
[Once proven to be forged, one more charge]
待证明其是伪造
[against you will be diminished.]
父亲的罪证就又少一条
[For the case of the Shen Family,]
当年沈府一案
[although the evidence was irrefutable,]
虽然证据确凿
[Deputy Minister Shen claimed innocence]
奈何沈侍郎一直喊冤
[and refused to sign the testament.]
不肯画押
[Despite enduring torture,]
历经刑讯
[he never confessed until his death.]
到死也没有认罪
[The case was closed with only]
最终结案只有物证
[physical evidence, no testimonies.]
没有口供
[But who could have foreseen]
可谁能料到
[that many years later,]
这多年之后
[with the young emperor on the throne,]
当今幼帝继位
[and the Empress Dowager in control,]
太皇太后临朝
[your esteemed husband Shen Du would]
你那好郎君沈渡
[go to great lengths to climb the ranks,]
为了摆脱罪籍爬上高位
[even writing a confession]
不惜写下了自白书
[on behalf of his father,]
替他父亲沈侍郎
[acknowledging all the crimes]
将当年的罪行
[from that time.]
一一地给认了
[Who is it?]
谁
[It's me.]
是我
[Your husband.]
你的夫君
[What are you up to?]
你怎么在这儿
[Why are you covered in blood?]
你怎么满身是血
[My darling,]
夫人
[do you want to know whose blood this is?]
你想知道这是谁的血吗
[It's the blood of your entire Yan family,]
就是你们颜家老少
[over a dozen lives.]
十几口的血
[As a spy,]
这都是你
[you deserve all this.]
你一个细作应得的
[Are you truly]
你真的是
[so cold-blooded and heartless?]
如此冷血无情之人吗
The porridge is quite good.
粥还不错
It's too sweet.
太甜
The side dishes are quite crunchy.
小菜还挺脆的
It's too salty.
太咸
I love this combo, so what?
我就爱吃甜粥配咸菜
Uncle Zhong,
忠叔
for future breakfasts,
以后的早食
make salty porridge with sweet dishes.
煮咸粥配甜点
Shen Du, what do you mean by this?
沈渡你什么意思
Nothing.
我没什么意思
Shen Du,
沈渡
is this truly your nature?
你便是这样的人吗
Is this truly the person you've become?
你真的就是这样的人吗
So what if it is?
是又如何
And if it isn't, what then?
不是又如何
Yan Xing,
颜幸
this is indeed my true nature.
我沈渡就是这样的人
Chief Shen,
大阁领
it's really unfair to you.
属下实在是为您不平
That woman is not just unsettled,
那女人不安分也就算了
but she's also a fierce one.
居然还是个母夜叉
She pretended to behave
刚开始的时候
in the beginning, but just
还知道做做样子
a few days in, her true colors showed.
这才几天啊就现了原形
[You have your duties to attend to,]
你有你的差要听
[and I have mine to fulfill.]
我也有我的差要交代
[I must at least put on a show.]
总得做做样子嘛
[But I won't go too far.]
但不会动真格的
[Don't worry.]
你放心吧
Jinglin,
景林
tell me,
你说
"Chief Shen's wife got beaten up by husband"
是大阁领夫人被夫君打
or "White Death married a fierce woman."
还是白无常
Which one would excite
遇上个母夜叉
the noble ladies of Xiang'an City,
更能让襄安城的
and make Lord Zhang and the likes
深宅贵女们兴奋
believe they could take advantage
让张相之流
of the situation?
觉得有机可乘
It's been several days since the wedding.
成亲之日已过去数日
Time for some gossip.
得让人有些谈资了
Are you suggesting
您是说
we deliberately let those
故意让那些
with ulterior motives believe
居心叵测之人
the Shen Family is unstable,
认定沈府家宅不宁
thereby lowering their guard?
从而放松警惕
You catch on quick.
还不算笨
So your argument with her today
所以您今日的吵架
was intentional?
是故意的
Brilliant!
妙啊
So my lady's injuries are
那夫人身上的伤
also part of your plan, right?
也是您故意设计的
The Imperial Academy has always admitted
弘文馆素来招的
individuals of high status.
都是品阶高的人士
This time, admission is based on merit,
此次招考并不附举荐信
not recommendations or family status.
对家世毫无考察
So how do they judge character?
又如何评判品行呢
Then it's about who writes better essays.
那就比谁文章写得好呗
Those country bumpkins,
那些乡野匹夫
as long as they are willing to work hard,
只要肯埋首苦背
and burn the midnight oil,
头悬梁 锥刺股
they might get lucky.
没准就能中了大奖
Once they enter the academy,
入了馆
I wouldn't want to study alongside them.
我可不愿和他们做同窗
Your Highness,
太皇太后
the examination at Imperial Academy is approaching.
弘文馆考学临近
It's the first time
这回
we've lowered the bars for social status.
是第一次放开家世考察
Scholars from humble backgrounds
寒门有学识
with talents and skills
有能力的学子
can all compete fairly.
皆能公平竞选
This is of great significance.
意义非同一般
Also, this time it's especially allowed
而且此次还特别允许
for students from Xichen and Nanlang
西辰和南琅的学子
to take the exam as well.
一同来考试
Therefore,
所以
every detail of this examination
这考试的桩桩件件事宜
must be handled meticulously.
皆不得马虎
Indeed,
是啊
Prime Minister Zhang is quite right.
张相说得极是
This examination is unprecedented
此次考学前所未有
and will affect the empire's reputation.
会影响我们大苍的脸面
Lord Zhang, who would you recommend
那张相你觉得
for this crucial assignment?
哪一位爱卿堪此重任啊
His Highness, Prince Xian, his efforts
贤王殿下
in disaster relief have been commendable.
此次赈灾功劳显著
The people have been singing his praises.
沿途百姓歌颂其清名
I believe
老臣认为
it would be wise to let him
此次不如就让贤王殿下
take charge of the imperial examinations.
来负责科考吧
Everyone knows that Prince Xian
世人皆知
and Prime minister Zhang favor the gentry.
贤王张相看重门阀
If you are in charge,
你们来负责
won't that mean humble families
那岂不是
will have no chance at all?
再无天下寒门半点机会
Sister, there's a misunderstanding.
皇姐误会了
Princess Ying,
那英王
who do you think is more fit for the role?
你觉得哪一位更合适呢
I believe
我看
Shen Du would be the best fit.
倒不如让沈渡来负责
Your Highness,
英王殿下
when did you start to favor
何时如此器重
Chief Shen?
沈大阁领了
Are you really suggesting
竟要让
that Imperial Guard, a military branch
负责武职的内卫府
should oversee the examinations?
去掌管文科考试
This is a misguided statement, Chancellor Lai.
来中丞此言差矣
Selecting the virtuous and capable is all
选贤举能
for the service of Her Royal Highness.
都是为太皇太后效力
Although the exam is a literary test,
弘文馆考学虽是文试
the relevant arrangements
可相关配置
require more than literary skills;
不止舞文弄墨
they also need strong leadership.
更是需要铁腕担当
The Imperial Guard is always meticulous.
内卫府做事向来仔细
It'll surely manage everything properly.
定能安排妥当
The Imperial Guard
内卫府
is at your service, Your Royal Highness.
愿为太皇太后分忧
We will do our utmost.
倾力一试
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
Chief Shen spends his days
这沈大阁领
arresting suspects and handling cases,
终日抓人办案
causing widespread anxiety.
闹得人人心惊
Moreover, the Shen household
而且沈府后宅
is embroiled in constant disputes,
又纷争不休
showing no signs of family harmony.
无齐家之相
If Shen Du is put in charge
若让沈渡来负责
of this imperial examination,
此次科考
it would truly be
那实在是
a disgrace to the royal family.
有辱斯文啊 太皇太后
As for the matters of my household,
沈某后宅之事
Prime Minister Zhang seems to know everything.
张相倒是清楚得很
Enough,
好了
about the examination,
这件事情
let me think it through.
让哀家再好好想想
- Your Royal Highness.
臣告退 儿臣告退
Who is it?
谁
Caiwei!
三姐
Please get up!
你快起来
Xing.
六娘
I am truly sorry.
是三姐对不起你
Caiwei,
三姐
why are you back?
你怎么回来了
Where is Mr. Han?
韩郎君呢
You've taken on the burden for me.
是你替姐姐受累了
Mr. Han and I have
我和韩郎商议
decided to return home to apologize.
索性一起回家请罪
But,
可是
I fear going home.
可我不敢回家
So I had to
就只好
hide outside the Shen residence.
只好躲在沈府外面
I'm sorry.
对不起
Caiwei,
三姐
stop blaming yourself.
你别自责了
Let's go home first.
我们先回家
Let's talk this out after we get home.
有什么事回家再说
Yeah, that side.
对对对 那边
Here, move it down a little.
来来来 下边下边下边
Yes.
对对对
OK.
好
Oh, get down here, now!
快下来 快下来
Xing and Caiwei are back!
三娘和六娘回来了
My lord, my lady!
老爷 夫人
Where is Caiwei?
三娘回来了
That's right.
是
Xing and Caiwei have returned!
三娘和六娘回来了
- Mother! - Caiwei!
娘 采薇
Caiwei, you're finally back!
采薇你可回来了
You've worried me sick!
你把娘担心死了
- Xing! - Mother!
六娘 阿娘
Oh, my poor little girl!
我苦命的六娘啊
So the rumors are true!
原来外面的传闻是真的
The White Death
那个白无常
indeed beat you up!
真的敢打你啊
Mother!
阿娘
You took someone else's burden
你好心好意
with good intentions,
替别人去闯阎王殿
but those ungrateful people
人家没良心的
have been living it up,
吃香喝辣母女团聚
while my poor girl
唯独我可怜的六娘
has been tormented by
被那个白无常威胁折磨
- the White Death. - Mother, please stop!
毒打啊 阿娘你别说了
No, I haven't.
没有
- It's all my... - Xing.
都怪 六娘
I was being selfish,
是我太自私了
only thinking of myself.
只想着自己
Today, outside the Shen residence,
今日在沈府外
I heard them talk about
我听他们说
how you were insulted by the White Death.
你被那白无常辱骂
I am in deep anguish to know that.
三姐心里痛苦万分
He even had the nerve to insult you!
那白无常还辱骂你啊
We were...
应该
insulting each other.
是互相辱骂
If something like this happens again,
下次再有这样的事
I'll go all out for you,
为娘豁出去了
and let's confront him together!
一起骂他
Mother, it really wasn't like that.
阿娘 真的没有
Everyone is here, huh?
大伙都在呢 大伙
Stop right here.
停 停停停 停
My sweet little sister,
六妹
I heard you got beat up
我听说你被那白无常
by the White Death.
给殴打了
Was it because
你就说是不是
you were being clumsy
因为你太蠢
so you couldn't serve him properly?
不会侍奉夫君
- Your temper is also bad. - Hey!
脾气又太臭 你
Pay attention to me! You little...
我给你说你还这 这
Caiwei?
三姐
It's really you, Caiwei!
真是你 三姐
Shut your mouth!
闭嘴吧
Didn't you run away with someone?
你不是跟人私奔了吗
You reek of alcohol,
一身酒气
staying out all night.
彻夜不归
This is unacceptable!
你成何体统
- Unacceptable! - Father!
老爷 成何体统 父亲
- My lord! - Unacceptable!
老爷 成何体统
My lord!
老爷
Get back to your room!
滚回屋去
Stop, please!
使不得 使不得呀
Father, I just remembered.
父 父亲 我想起来了
On my way back,
我刚才回来的路上
I think I saw the White Death
好像看见那个白 白无常
leading a group of guardsmen
带着一队内卫
heading towards our residence.
冲咱家来了
Will they arrest someone, I wonder?
不知道要抓谁
Greetings, Chief Shen.
参见大阁领
Chief Shen.
大阁领
Shen Du.
沈渡
It's all my fault,
这一切都是我的错
and it has nothing to do with Xing.
与六娘无关
Just take it out on me.
有什么都冲着我来好了
Who are you?
你是谁
Yan Caiwei?
颜采薇
Take her away!
带走
Chief Shen,
大阁领
I fully understand the marriage
老夫深知
between the Shen and Yan families
沈颜两家联姻
has caused some discomfort for you.
令大阁领心有不快
I also feel a sense of guilt.
老夫也心有愧疚
However, the marriage between you and Xing
但是大阁领与六娘
has already been established.
婚事已成
I hope you could
还望大阁领
show some leniency for the sake
看在婚事的面上
of this union, Chief Shen.
网开一面呀 大阁领
Take Yan Xing
颜幸
away as well!
也带走
Both of them, Chief Shen?
两个人都带走 大阁领
Please don't!
大阁领 不可呀 大阁领
Don't you touch them!
不许动
I, Yan Mojie, am here,
我颜墨杰在此
and don't you lay a finger on us!
谁也不许碰我颜家人
The White Death,
白无常
do you really believe
你真以为
you are from hell?
你是阎王殿的是不是
So you could just
你想勾走谁的魂
take anyone as you please?
你就带走谁
Where's the justice in this?
还有没有王法了
Shut your mouth!
你给我闭嘴
This pig
这个东西
is obstructing official business.
妨碍公务
Take it away!
一块带走
Chief Shen!
大阁领
Mercy, Chief Shen!
手下留情啊 大阁领
Please don't take them, Chief Shen!
大阁领不可呀 大阁领
Chief Shen, please!
大阁领啊 大阁领
Have some mercy, my lord!
手下留情啊 大阁领
- Caiwei! Xing! - Chief Shen!
采薇 六娘 大阁领
Chief Shen, please!
大阁领啊 不可呀
Chief Shen.
大阁领
Shen Du,
沈渡
what exactly do you want?
你到底想干吗
Yan Caiwei,
颜采薇
where is Han Shiyuan?
韩世元在哪儿
I...
我
I don't know.
我不知道
He is now a murder suspect.
他如今是杀人嫌犯
Are you sure you want to cover for him?
你确定要包庇他
What?
什么 什么
My lady, you didn't
夫人
show up at the Ministry of Justice today,
您今日未去刑部
so you may not know.
有所不知
In a well at the Imperial Academy,
弘文馆的一口偏井中
the body of a student was discovered.
发现了一名学子的尸体
This case involves
因此案涉及到
students from the Imperial Academy,
弘文馆学子
which agitated Her Royal Highness.
惊动了太皇太后
Her Royal Highness ordered
太皇太后
the Imperial Guard to investigate.
指明由内卫府来查办
And currently, the prime suspect
而目前最大的嫌疑人
is Han Shiyuan.
便是韩世元
Impossible!
不可能
He would never commit murder!
韩郎他绝不可能杀人
Do you think Han Shiyuan was
你以为韩世元与你是
running away with you for love?
为爱远走天涯
But the evidence shows he was fleeing
但证据显示
for fear of being charged with murder.
他是杀人畏罪潜逃
How could this be happening?
怎么会
This is simply impossible!
不可能
Caiwei,
三姐
you genuinely don't know
你当真不知道
where Han Shiyuan is?
韩世元身在何处
He must show up
他必须现身
to prove his innocence.
才能证明自己的清白
As soon as we returned to Xiang'an,
我们一回到襄安
he disappeared.
韩郎他就不见了
I...
我
I truly don't know.
我真的不知道
May I take a look
我可以去看一下
at the body of the deceased?
死者的尸体吗
There are no signs of drowning
尸体的口鼻内
in the mouth and nose,
并无呛水痕迹
so we can rule out suicide by drowning.
排除溺水自杀
The corpse shows multiple bruises,
身上有多处皮肉挫伤
indicating signs of a struggle.
有打斗痕迹
The estimated time of death
死亡时间
was probably a month ago.
约莫将近一个月
My lady, the time of death
夫人
should be around the seventh of May.
死亡时间应为五月初七
Thank you.
多谢
Your coroner is truly remarkable
内卫府的仵作就是厉害
and able to deduce such precise details.
居然能推测得如此精准
I'm quite impressed.
佩服佩服
It seems that
看来
I still have much to learn
我还得多跟你们
from all of you.
学习学习
My lady
夫人
and her
和她那个
whining sister
哭哭啼啼的姐姐
are truly different.
还真是不一样啊
Why are you all standing so far away?
你们站得那么远
Are you worried the body might decompose
是怕尸体会过度腐化
and suddenly burst open?
突然炸开吗
Don't worry.
不用担心
The decomposition isn't
腐化程度还未到
at that stage yet.
不会炸开的
This is just too unusual.
这也太过于不一样了
Is there any other evidence?
还有什么别的证物吗
We also retrieved
从井下
a piece of clothing
还捞出来一块衣服碎片
and a scroll from the well.
和一卷书简
Upon examination,
经查验
the clothing belongs to Han Shiyuan,
衣服是韩世元的
and the scroll
而这书简
was left by the instructor
是初七当日
as a quiz
弘文馆的夫子
at the Imperial Academy on the seventh.
留下的堂后测验
Thus,
所以
the date of death
死亡日期
is inferred from this evidence.
就是根据这个推测的
The information about the deceased
死者信息的获取
is gathered through more than
可不止仵作验尸
just the coroner's examination.
一种方式
The Imperial Guard is on duty!
内卫府办案
Where is Han Shiyuan?
韩世元在哪儿
I don't know.
我不知道
Hey, you!
你
Where is Han Shiyuan?
韩世元在哪儿
I don't know either.
我也不知道
No one knows, huh?
不说是吧
Jinglin!
景林
Is this how you conduct investigation?
哪有你这么问的
Are you trying to force a confession?
屈打成招吗
They are almost scared to death!
人都快被吓死了
Get out of here!
快出去
I almost got it! I...
我差点就问出来了 我
Let me do the talking.
我来问
My lady must have forgotten that
夫人怕不是忘了
she's also in a uniform.
自己也穿着刑部衣服吧
He was quite introverted
平常里很低调
and didn't interact much with us.
和我们交流都不多
May I ask,
请问
have you seen Han Shiyuan
你这段时日
in recent days?
可有看过韩世元
The last time I saw Han Shiyuan
最后一次看到韩世元
was in the evening of the seventh of May.
是在五月初七的晚上
That day, I passed by his room and saw him
那天我从他寝室路过
saying goodbye to his classmates,
看他和同窗告别后
and then he left.
然后就出门了
Seventh of May, evening.
五月初七的晚上
How can you be so sure?
你这么肯定
He went west when he left.
那天他出门往西走
I was just about to greet him,
我正要和他打招呼呢
but when I turned around,
结果一扭头
I saw the firelight in the east.
就看到了东边的火光
Then I heard about
再然后
the fire at the Ming Hall.
就听说了明堂大火
That's why I remember.
所以记得
Han Shiyuan is one of the most
韩世元是我们馆中
good looking students in our academy.
数一数二的俊俏学子
He doesn't interact much with others.
平常跟大家很少有来往
By the way,
对了
you can ask
你可以问问
his roommate, Lan Guizhou.
他同寝的兰桂舟
But Lan Guizhou is a man
不过兰桂舟这个人
who is always reserved and gloomy.
向来内敛沉闷
He only speaks to Han Shiyuan.
他只同韩世元讲话的
Are you Lan Guizhou?
你是兰桂舟吗
I am Lan Guizhou.
我是兰桂舟
On the seventh of May,
五月初七
did you see Han Shiyuan?
你可见过韩世元
I did.
见过
Shiyuan mentioned that
世元说
he was leaving Xiang'an to get married.
他要离开襄安回去成婚
After saying his farewells, he went west.
话别之后就向西去了
Alright, thank you.
好 多谢
Lady!
姐姐
Is there anything I can assist with?
有什么我可以帮忙的吗
You are just everywhere, aren't you?
怎么哪儿都有你呀
I'm here to collect
我来收
the pawned items from the students.
学子的典当之物啊
Investigating a case
查案
requires getting involved
就得像姐姐一样
just like my lady does.
深入一线
The way my lady investigates
我姐姐查案的样子
is truly something to behold!
真是英姿飒爽
When will I be able to
什么时候
apprentice under her
我才能拜她为师
and follow her in investigations?
跟着查案
Lady!
姐姐
No one
任何人
is allowed to disturb clerk Yan
不得妨碍颜书吏
while she focuses on the investigation.
专心查案
What's on your mind?
在担心什么
I just feel something is off.
我只是觉得有点不对劲
Anything wrong with the evidence?
证据有问题
No.
没有
But it's precisely because there isn't any
但就是因为没有
that I find it a bit strange.
我才觉得有点奇怪
It's too perfect.
太完美了
Look. Take a look.
你来看 来看
Eyewitnesses and evidence are too complete
人证和物证都太过完备
to the point that it feels a bit contrived.
以至于感觉有点刻意
Investigations can't solely rely on hunch.
查案不能只靠感觉
I only trust evidence.
我只相信证据
Me too.
我也相信证据
But what if the evidence is fabricated?
但如果证据是假的呢
Look here.
你看这儿
And here.
还有这儿
What are you doing?
你干吗
It's too dark.
太暗
It's not dark at all, alright?
哪里暗了
This room is practically bright as day!
这屋里简直亮如白昼
I find it blinding, honestly!
我都觉得刺眼好吗
Let's see the physical evidence first.
先说物证
There are scrolls and pieces of clothing.
又是书简又是衣服残片
These two pieces of evidence
这两个证据
seem to be trying to ensure
好像生怕查不到
that Han Shiyuan is implicated.
韩世元头上
That clothing from Han Shiyuan,
韩世元的那件衣服
the color is so distinct.
颜色那么明显
If it were torn,
若是撕掉了
how could it not be noticed?
怎么会看不出来呢
And check this out,
你再看这个
these two students as witnesses
这两个学子人证
both said they saw Han Shiyuan
都说五月初七的夜里
on the night of the seventh of May,
见过韩世元
and they were very certain.
而且非常笃定
But that day was our wedding day.
可那天是我们结亲之日
Caiwei and Han Shiyuan
三姐和韩世元
had already run away on the sixth of May.
在五月初六就已经跑了
They might have run away just to
跑了可能只是为了
avoid your Yan Family.
躲着你们颜家
Perhaps, on the seventh of May,
说不定
they were still in the city,
五月初七还在城中
watching you idiot get married.
看着你这个傻子替嫁
No way.
不会
Caiwei and Han Shiyuan
我三姐跟韩世元
had already left the city
在我们结亲之前
before our wedding.
就已经出城了
You trust her so much.
这么相信你三姐
Then why did she let you take her place?
那她为什么让你替嫁
Caiwei...
我三姐
had no choice either.
不也是没有办法吗
Who would want to marry
谁愿意嫁给
you, the White Death?
你这个白无常
Oh really?
这么委屈
Then you should leave.
那你也走
Hell doesn't welcome you either.
阎罗殿也不欢迎你
Fine by me.
走就走
Good, good!
好 好 好
Bravo!
好好好
Wonderful!
精彩 精彩
Do it again!
再来一个
Bravo!
真棒
Here it comes!
来了来了
The hanging ghost comes to kill!
吊死鬼上门索命了
Good!
好
Look!
快看快看
Bust!
收
The ghost has been busted!
鬼被收了
So magical!
好神通啊
Incredible!
太厉害了
Good, good.
好 好 好
I don't have any magical powers.
我哪有什么神通啊
This is just
这只不过
the most ordinary sleight of hand.
是最寻常的障眼法罢了
I'm operating the mechanism inside,
我在里面操作机关
pulling it down.
向下操作
What appears on this white cloth
那这白布上呈现的
is the image going up.
就是向上的图影
Everyone, remember,
大家切记
if in the future
若是以后
someone claims to use this technique
有人说能借此法术
to catch ghosts,
诓骗大家抓鬼
that person must be a con artist.
此人定是江湖骗子
So that's how it is.
原来是这样
Now I understand.
现在知道了
You revealed the trick just like that.
你这么直接揭秘拆台
Aren't you afraid of ruining your peers'
就不怕砸了同行的饭碗
livelihoods? They might cause you trouble.
他们找你麻烦
Mozi said,
墨子曰
the view manifests,
景到
come noon it takes shape and extends;
在午有端与景长
the essence rests in its form.
说在端
This is a principle known
这是古人千百年前
by the ancients for thousands of years.
就知道的道理
So anyone who reads
所以但凡是读书之人
should be familiar with it.
我想都应知晓此事
Therefore, it is not a secret.
所以这也不是什么机密
It should not be used to deceive
更不应该诓骗
the common folks.
那些老百姓
You, sir,
你这位郎君
are quite interesting.
倒是有趣得很
Although you make a living in the market,
看你虽然身在鬼市
you are a scholar with integrity.
却是个有风骨的读书人
I just heard that the Imperial Academy
我只是听闻这弘文馆
accepts students
不论门第
regardless of background,
开科取士
so I came to join the fun.
我呢就来凑个热闹
I see.
原来如此
I wish you success in getting enrolled.
那先预祝郎君高中
I usually enjoy reading casual books,
我就平时好读闲书
but when it comes to classics,
看到经史子集
I can't really get into them.
我也根本就看不进去
So
倒是
I'm afraid I won't be able to meet
怕是入不了
the standards of the Imperial Academy.
这弘文馆的法眼
I could only make a living
也就只能在这鬼市
in this night market.
讨些营生了
You're being overly modest, sir.
郎君自谦了
I see you have quite a bit of knowledge
我看你对这光影之术
about this light and shadow technique.
很有研究
I actually have a matter
倒有一事
I wish to inquire about.
想要请教
My lady, you are being overly humble.
不敢不敢
Just call me Pan.
叫我阿潘就行
If you have any questions,
小娘子如若有事
feel free to ask, my fair lady.
但说无妨
Whether it's self-defense techniques
无论是防身之术
or ways to manage a husband,
又或是御夫之道
I know a thing or two.
我都略知一二
I don't need those.
这些我都不用
About your mechanism,
看你这个机关
there are no ghosts inside,
本来无鬼
yet it seems as if there are.
却恍若有鬼
Do you know if there's a way
那你可知
to make it seem like someone is inside,
有什么办法
while there's actually no one.
能让屋里没有人
And the people outside
屋外之人
think they see someone?
却觉得看到了他
In this world, there are no ghosts,
这世上本无鬼神
and no one knows
也没人知道
what ghosts really look like.
鬼神真正的样子
But living people are different.
但活人就不一样了
People have different appearances.
活人样貌各不同
To disguise oneself,
想要伪装
is not easy at all.
谈何容易
Exactly.
正是
My fair lady,
这样
why don't you elaborate on
小娘子不妨将你所问
your question?
展开说说
For example, the time,
比如时辰
the light,
光线
the orientation in the room,
屋内方位
or the appearances of people
或是屋内屋外之人
inside and outside the room, and so on.
相貌等等
OK.
好
Bravo!
好 好
What are you doing in here?
来内卫府做什么
I found the proof.
我找到证据了
Han Shiyuan is innocent.
韩世元是被冤枉的
What proof?
什么证据
Come with me to the academy tonight.
晚上跟我去弘文馆
You'll catch the culprit right there.
我让你当场缉凶